All right, בוקר טוב, boker tov, we start a new מסכת masechet
today, סוטה. Sotah. Our דף daf
is ב, beis,
and one or two quick words about the מסכת. masechet. Thank God
we now have back to our real רש״י, Rashi, which means that
just have the wonderful benefit of רש״י's Rashi's like you really get
to appreciate רש״י Rashi when you don't have him for a while,
you know sort of you know very distilled and clear you know
commentary to the גמרא, Gemara, but that also allows for is for
there to be a more real תוספות. Tosafos. Because when תוספות Tosafos
had to do the work of רש״י, Rashi, which is basically what
תוספות Tosafos had to do in נזיר, Nazir, there was not as
much of an opportunity for תוספות Tosafos to do much more than
clarify what was going on on the דף daf itself, rather than
ask more of sort of like broad questions in terms of comparing
to other סוגיות, sugyos, you know or just more sort of like
broadly analytic types of questions. So that's very nice, and
there's another תוספות Tosafos here along the side, but what it also
does mean is that there's more גמרא Gemara per דף, daf, because
when you have תוספות Tosafos that are so long when you have
the pseudo-רש״י Rashi is doing his own job of commentating and not
doing as
terse as רש״י, Rashi, and then you have תוספות Tosafos which is
taking on רש״י's Rashi's responsibility but also in a much longer way,
so much of you know the pseudo-רש״י Rashi and the תוספות Tosafos
are filling up the דף daf in terms of the just explaining
what's going on, whereas here, because you know רש״י Rashi sort of
gives you the base explanation and therefore תוספות Tosafos can focus on
these more critical questions,
there's less of רש״י Rashi there's less you know of there's less
in terms of the comment of the base commentary because רש״י Rashi
does such a good job being terse and to the point, and
there's less תוספות Tosafos because תוספות Tosafos is now really focused on
a much more narrowly defined task. So the דפים dappin look more
like standard דפים dappin of the גמרא, Gemara, there's a lot more
גמרא Gemara per דף daf and there's also a lot of אגדתא.
aggadeta. And so if you just glance ahead you know here like
on דף יא daf yud-aleph whatever you can just see because like
a דף daf like this, right on דף טו daf tes-vav טז
tes-zayin right you know there's a lot so, so that's two reasons
why there's a lot more גמרא Gemara per דף daf so I'll
have to talk faster.
So that's just in terms of what's in terms of like the
structure of the גמרא. Gemara. In terms of what the גמרא Gemara
covers, as advertised it deals with the פרשת סוטה Parshat Sotah in
the תורה Torah and we'll deal right away with sort of its
placement in סדר נשים. Seder Nashim. And the first like eight פרקים
perakim or so not eight pretty much the first six פרקים perakim
are just dealing with the procedure of under what circumstances is a
woman declared a סוטה, sotah, a woman suspected of having committed adultery
that would necessitate going through the process of having of being brought
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and drinking from the water etc.
And once it's decided what are the circumstances in which a woman
is a סוטה sotah then it gets onto the procedure of the
bringing of the of the drinking of the water and how would
that ritual go, and then the bringing of the sacrifices and how
would that ritual go, what could be the various consequences of those
rituals, what about special
cases let's say a woman is a שומרת יבם shomeres yabam would
it be the same הלכה halakha as and who's suspected of committing
adultery would it be the same הלכה halakha as a wife, let's
say she's an ארוסה arusah not a נשואה. nesuah. So then it
also deals with special cases but you know very logical structure and
almost sequen almost you know sequential type of a of a treatment
of the issue starting from her being suspected to her being brought
to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So as you know from other
מסכתות masechtot it doesn't always follow that type of a sequential sort
of proce you know sort of order in terms of the מסכת.
masechet. And then the last two in particular are very interesting or
last three because it starts with the seventh פרק perek about אלו
נאמרים בכל לשון. eilu ne'emarim bechol lashon. Because there's a question whether
פרשת סוטה Parshat Sotah you know or whether the recitation of סוטה
Sotah is said בכל לשון bechol lashon or not. And therefore it
gets this becomes an opportunity to talk about all various types of
ritual acts of speech whether it's קריאת שמע Kriat Shema or תפילה
tefillah or whether it's ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim or a whole wide
range, can they be set must they be said only in Hebrew
or can they be said in any language. So that becomes a
real then interesting opportunity to explore all these different מצוות mitzvot related
to speech and whether again you can use other languages and this
opportunity to explore other aspects of them as well. In particular the
last פרק perek is about עגלה ערופה. eglah arufah. The breaking of
the neck of the heifer where there's a murder you don't know
who did it and it starts with the question about whether that's
said בכל לשון. bechol lashon. But then it uses that as an
opportunity to discuss what exactly is the ritual of עגלה ערופה, eglah
arufah, when do you do it how do you measure the most
nearby city you know all of its different parameters because there's no
other place in מסכת masechet well it could have been in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin I suppose but because סנהדרין Sanhedrin is more about prosecuting the
murderer when you find
him whereas here it
is
Whereas, you know, here it's about not knowing, so this is the
opportunity in ש"ס, Shas, the one place in ש"ס Shas where it
discusses the parameters of עגלה ערופה, Egla Arufa, and I think that
it's not just coincidental like, oh, there was no other place to
discuss it and we have the hook of קול השון. Kol Ha-shon.
I also think it's because עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa like what do
you call it, like סוטה, Sotah, I mean, is a case where
what is a ritual that you do when you don't know if
some serious type of an offense has been committed? Right? So both
of them are in a sense rituals that are done in the
case of doubt. So I think that's another reason why that's there.
So that's going to be an interesting like end to the מסכת.
Masechet. Right,
right, that is correct. Well, that's a good point, that's a good
point. In one case you know what happened, you don't know who
did it, and in the other case the basic question is you
know who the suspected parties are, you don't know if something happened
or not.
You don't even know if the person was murdered, he may have
just died.
That's true, I mean, right, it's that's true, but the way the
תורה Torah does describe it, it does sound like it's clear that
a murder did occur, but right. Okay. All right. So, all right,
I don't know what the heck is happening here whether this is
working or not. So let's keep on going. So the,
so let's start now with the משנה, Mishna, okay? המקנא לאשתו, Hamakaneh
le'ishto, if a man is now מקנא makaneh here becomes an interesting
verb which the גמרא Gemara is going to get to because the
way the תורה Torah describes it is איש איש כי תשטה אשתו,
ish ish ki tisteh ishto,
so a man's wife has gone wayward and then we're about, you
know, and then it sort of becomes clear that he's suspecting this
and it says וקנא את אשתו והיא נטמאה ve-kina es ishto ve-hi
nitma'ah או כי o ki what's it? איש איש כי תשטה אשתו
ish ish ki tisteh ishto ומעלה בו מעל u-ma'ala bo ma'al ועבר
עליו רוח קנאה, ve-avar alav ruach kina, a spirit of jealousy passed
by, וקנא את אשתו והיא נטמאה ve-kina es ishto ve-hi nitma'ah או
עבר עליו רוח קנאה וקנא את אשתו והיא לא נטמאה. o avar
alav ruach kina ve-kina es ishto ve-hi lo nitma'ah. So he's jealous.
Is he right or is he wrong? We don't know, but he's
jealous. Okay, and then the תורה Torah goes on to say that
what does he do? He brings his wife for this ritual of
the סוטה. Sotah. So actually, and it's really important to mention this
at the outset, that what, that it's going one really interesting thing
to note in terms of
how the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh frames סוטה Sotah is
that what it does is it takes a, how it sort of,
you know, diverges from the simple פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim.
Because I would say there are two places, you know, most obvious
that come to mind where the תורה Torah sort of allows for
what could be, you know, a less of a judicial system and
more, well, one case is the vigilante justice of the גואל הדם,
goel ha-dam, right? So there, right, where somebody's, you know, where the
redeemer of blood, a relative was murdered, you go and you murder
and whatever in response, and there it's clear that the תורה Torah
is sort of tempering the reality of
גואל הדם. goel ha-dam. It doesn't, it doesn't sort of eliminate it,
but it brings in the judicial structure. It has the person be
sent to the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, ושלחו משם, ve-shalchu mi-sham, and
then the בית דין beis din right takes over and they basically
bring the guy back from the עיר מקלט ir miklat and they
do a normal judicial type of a proceedings, right? And if he
gets killed in a way that violates this procedure by the גואל
הדם goel ha-dam then the גואל הדם goel ha-dam has committed
murder. Nevertheless, in certain cases,
if the guy is outside of the עיר מקלט ir miklat when
he shouldn't be, right, so then the גואל הדם goel ha-dam can
kill him without, you know, with impunity, and according to some תנאים
Tannaim he even has a מצוה mitzvah to kill him. So it's
an interesting, you know, balance moving away from this vigilante tribal type
of justice to a judicial system, but nevertheless, you know, it hasn't,
it hasn't been completely eliminated. So what you have, that's in the
פסוקים pesukim themselves. So what you have by סוטה, Sotah, right, so
you have something that in the simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim
there's absolutely no evidence. וקנא את אשתו ve-kina es ishto and he,
he's jealous. Who knows what, what she did? Maybe, he says, so
he goes and he שלעפס schleps her to the בית המקדש Beis
Ha-Mikdash and we're going to now have this ritual. So it's completely,
he has that power or ability just because he's jealous. Doesn't need
any evidence, completely subjective. What חז"ל Hazal do with how they interpret
it though is קנא kinei becomes the whole thing becomes judicial,
judicialized, I don't know, anyway, the whole thing becomes sort of brought
into a judicial system, no but I mean more than that, just
the whole whole system is brought into a judicial context and the
וקנא את אשתו ve-kina es ishto becomes almost, you know, a concrete
act of laying groundwork to create sufficient sort of circumstantial evidence
to a legal- like a legal act that's going to give us
the basis now for saying that there's reason to think that good
circumstantial evidence that she might have committed adultery and now therefore we
can process this and continue to take this further. So it does
a sort of amazing thing, not just in terms of, you know,
not just in terms of like sort of making those demands that
there be that the circumstantial evidence be that foundation be laid, but
taking this verb, the קנא את אשתו, kina et ishto, which is
purely about his own subjective jealousy, and turning it into a almost
like a judicial act, okay, or you know a very concrete act
that creates objective circumstantial evidence. So that's sort of so let's take
a look about how that plays out. But that's the word מקנא
לאשתו mikaneh le'ishto is going to be an act of warning one's
wife not to be in private with another man and as we'll
see in the משנה, mishna, and warning her in the presence of
witnesses. So it's actually a formal act that creates you know this
context. Okay. A specific right, a specific man. Don't be in private
with this specific man and she's being warned in the presence of
witnesses and this is called being מקנא לאשתו. mikaneh le'ishto. Okay? So
and by the way, notice also the difference of the preposition. In
the תורה Torah it is וקינא את אשתו, ve'kina et ishto, right?
And it's מקנא לאשתו mikaneh le'ishto because here it shifts from being
jealous about his wife to warning his wife, admonishing his wife. Okay,
yeah.
The way it sounds in the תורה Torah though, it sounds like
she's guilty and you know it's just a technicality that he can't
pursue.
Well, that's the other thing in the תורה. Torah.
The תורה- Torah no, no, no, but listen, this is how it's
introduced. You just- you said it, you skipped this whole part of
איש איש כי תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל ושכב איש אותה שכבת
זרע ונעלם מעיני אישה ונסתרה והיא נטמאה ועד אין בה והיא לא
נתפשה.
ish ish ki tisteh ishto u'ma'alah bo ma'al ve'shachav
ish
otah shichvat zera ve'ne'elam me'einei ishah ve'nistarah ve'hi nitma'ah ve'ed ein bah
ve'hi lo nitpasah. That's how it's like right, right, introduced.
Someone slept with her but her husband didn't know and she was
like you know secretive and closeted but there's no you know right,
there's no witness. Then it says oh he's going to be קנא
kina maybe and she was נטמאה nitma'ah oh maybe she wasn't. You
know what I mean? But the way you know
I think what Michael's saying is absolutely correct. I think the פשט
pshat of the פסוקים psukim is there's a presumption of guilt. So
it's not only that he's entitled due to his jealousy and there's
no evidence mentioned in the פסוקים psukim and not even circumstantial, there's
an automatic presumption of guilt and in a way she needs the
ritual to you know remove her from that presumption of guilt but
why was there that presumption?
From knowing the נסתרה nistarah part it would be
the next part of oh and he warned her. Right, right. Look,
it is true. Okay, we can debate this. I agree with Michael
that it is sort of saying like, okay, we assume she's guilty,
maybe she didn't do it, but the basic meaning just- I- yes,
I think he's right. It says here's what happened or maybe she
didn't do it. But anyway you could anyway- the interesting thing to
read is according to הלכה halacha and which is not clear in
the פסוקים, psukim, once a woman is a סוטה, sotah, she has
a status of טמאה tmeiah and she is forbidden to continue to
sleep or to have sex with her
husband, her husband's forbidden to continue to have sex with her. She
actually has a status of as if she had committed adultery until
her status is clarified through the ritual in the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. So again, that also reflects almost like this presumption of guilt
until it's clarified about- the way the גמרא's Gemara going to understand
it is because we've laid this groundwork of circumstantial evidence. But I
do agree you know at least whatever we can debate that but
I agree with Michael.
On another level you might consider this as just in his imagination
she...
right, that's a good point, meaning, meaning ושכב איש אותה ve'shachav ish
otah is like here is what he has imagined. Right, that's a
good point, that's a good point. That it might be describing like
these are the images that are you know that are right, this
is his- this is what is right, exactly, this is what's you
know filling his head.
Yeah the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim to me always suggested
that this entire ritual is for the benefit of the man's assuaging
his like clarifying or assuaging his jealousy. Right. What you're describing is
it's a ritual that's necessitated by the real possibility that she's an
adulteress.
Look, I think we can discuss that. I mean I do think
it- on the one hand the פסוקים psukim do not make clear
do not make clear what the הלכה halacha later says, which is
that she has a status of being טמאה tmeiah until the ritual.
So if she doesn't have that status, you could say that it's
just the man's jealousy and we're just dealing with his jealousy. On
the other hand, I do want to sort of say to back
up you know Michael's read of the פסוקים psukim is that when
the כהן kohen makes- makes her swear, the כהן kohen says
ואת כי שטית ושכב איש אותך... ve'at ki satit ve'shachav ish otach...
like he basically presents it as- as if this happened when he
makes her take that oath as well. So I- I- I- do
think that there's a sense that we really do suspect or maybe
even we assume that that... So anyway, but the- but גמרא Gemara
here, the הלכה halacha reframes this as laying circumstantial evidence. so evidence
and as a formal act of
מקנא לאשתו mekane le-ishto warning the wife. Let's take a look. And,
by the way, I should say that the last that נזיר Nazir
ended with a whole series of משניות mishnayot about רגליים לדבר raglayim
la-davar and when you have circumstantial evidence and basis to assume, and
that's generally, although that word is not used in this משנה, mishnah,
seems to be the point about סוטה Sotah is רגליים לדבר, raglayim
la-davar, and that phrase does come up soon enough. So that might
have been an intentional way of segueing from נזיר Nazir to סוטה
Sotah is רגליים לדבר. raglayim la-davar. Let's take a look. See, we
haven't gotten past the first two
words. המקנא לאשתו, Ha-mekane le-ishto, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, מקנא
לה על פי שנים, mekane lah al pi shenayim, he warns her
in the presence of two
witnesses, ומשקה על פי עד אחד u-mashkah al pi ed echad by
one witness. Because it's not enough to warn. What חז"ל Chazal also
read in is he warned her, but then what happens afterwards? Where's
the circumstantial evidence? So then there's another event that occurred, which is
ונסתרה, ve-nisterah, ונטמאה. ve-nitme'ah. And now that is in the פסוקים, pesukim,
right? Because the פסוקים pesukim do say, what is it? ונסתרה והיא
נטמאה, ve-nisterah ve-hi nitme'ah, או עבר עליו רוח קנאה וקנא את אשתו.
o avar alav ruach kinah ve-kina et ishto. No, it only says...
it doesn't say ונסתרה והיא לא נטמאה, ve-nisterah ve-hi lo nitme'ah, right?
It just says ונסתרה והיא נטמאה. ve-nisterah ve-hi nitme'ah.
Right.
ונסתרה והיא נטמאה. ve-nisterah ve-hi nitme'ah. Right. So in the פסוקים, pesukim,
it's not clear that she objectively was נסתרה nisterah and the question
is what happened. You could read the פסוקים pesukim like he suspects
that she was נסתרה ונטמאה, ve-nisterah ve-nitme'ah, but maybe there's no evidence
that anything happened. So the other thing that חז"ל Chazal do is
they not only make קנאת אשתו, kinat ishto, warning her in a
formal judicial and a formal act, but then נסתרה nisterah is objectively
known. And because נסתרה nisterah is objectively known, that she was in
private with this man, with the backdrop that she was specifically warned
against going into private with this man, that then becomes the basis
for this concern.
Another way of saying then is that if there was no עד
ed at all about the סתירה, stirah, one way or the other,
then she can't...
Well, let's take a look. It might depend on which position of
the
תנאים Tannaim you adopt. It says ואין עד בה. ve-ein ed bah.
Right.
In the פסוק, pasuk, there's no direct evidence.
Right. But the point what חז"ל Chazal do is they say ונסתרה,
ve-nisterah, that is like, that is known as a, right? In the
פסוק, pasuk, ונסתרה ve-nisterah could still just be his imagination. Right? But
what חז"ל Chazal do is not only they say קנא kina means
to warn in front of witnesses, but they say נסתרה nisterah then
becomes also an established fact. And there are those two stages: being
warned and then סתירה, stirah, and then being in private. So let's
one more time. המקנא לאשתו, Ha-mekane le-ishto, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, מקנא לה על פי שנים, mekane lah al pi shenayim, warned
in front of two, ומשקה על פי עד אחד או על פי
עצמו. u-mashkah al pi ed echad o al pi atzmo. But here,
to make her drink, to say that she's violated this warning and
gone in private, that suffices if there's even one witness or even
his own testimony. So here actually it's not so objective. He still
has to say that he actually directly observed it. He can't just
say he suspects her. But nevertheless, even he himself, according to רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, is believed to say that she went into private.
And that wouldn't work in regular jurisprudence. I can't be the...
Right, obviously not. But here it is. But so here, so that
definitely does make it more him, but he's not just suspecting, he's
making at least
a claim. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, מקנא לה על פי
שנים ומשקה על פי שנים. mekane lah al pi shenayim u-mashkah al
pi shenayim. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua makes it has as most objective
as possible. The warning has to be in front of two and
her going into private to allow to then be able to force
her to drink also has to be in front of two.
And he can't be one of them.
Correct. כיצד מקנא לה? Keitzad mekane lah? How does he warn her?
אומר לה בפני שנים, Omer lah bifnei shenayim, because that's not debated.
Both רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say the
warning is in front of two. He says in front of two,
אל תדברי עם איש פלוני, Al tidberi im ish peloni, do not
speak with so and so. Now, that seems presumably... there's always an
interesting question here about what phrase is a
euphemism. And תדברי tidberi sometimes is a euphemism for sex, but presumably
he's saying no, I don't even want you speaking to this
guy. ודיברה עמו. Ve-dibrah imo. Now she violates that and she goes
ahead and she speaks to the guy. עדיין היא מותרת לביתה, Adayin
hi muteret le-veitah, she's permissible to her house, meaning to have sex
with her
husband, ומותרת לאכול בתרומה. u-muteret le-echol bi-terumah. If she's the wife of
a כהן, kohen, she can eat תרומה. terumah. Because again, if she
had committed adultery, or if she has a status of a
סוטה Sotah for which we'll treat her as if she committed adultery
until it's clarified, she can't have sex with her husband and as
the wife of a כהן kohen can't eat תרומה. terumah.
So we explicitly make sure that תדבר tidber here is not sex.
Exactly. Exactly. So that, right. So if just because she violated that
would not make her a סוטה. Sotah. So what makes her a
סוטה Sotah is not just the violating, but the going into
private, ונסתרה. ve-nisterah. נכנסה עמו לבית הסתר, Nichnesah imo le-veit ha-seter, if
she went with him into a private
location, ושהתה עמו כדי טומאה, ve-shahatah imo kedei tumah, and stayed there
the length of time that it would take to have sex, כדי
טומאה. kedei tumah. You've got this based on the
פסוק pasuk of
ונטמאה. ve-nitme'ah. through this ritual in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, she
can't have sex with her husband, she can't eat תרומה, Trumah, ומת,
v'meit, and let's say the husband dies before the whole ritual is
done, so now there's no way to do the ritual because the
husband's dead, you need a husband alive to do the ritual, okay,
so is she the status of a woman who committed adultery or
not? So she's a ספק safek and חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzet v'lo
mityabemet. So if there's a living brother and there was no children
from this marriage, you can do חליצה chalitza you can't do ייבום
yibbum because ייבום yibbum would not be permitted in the case where
the woman had committed adultery, okay, and we'll find out about that.
So let's bracket the ייבום. yibbum.
Yeah,
I do think, I didn't go back and check, I do think
סוטה Sotah came up once or twice in מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot.
It was a while ago, but here it's looking at it from
the other end.
Yeah, so the basicness, I mean, if you're too close to eve,
if he said more than one person, then it wouldn't be
valid, you said אל תסתרי לפלוני או פלוני al tistari l'ploni o
ploni and then right, so that's like can you combine two separate,
is that considered two separate קינות kinot combined at once? Right, you
know, if he said don't peek
to, you can't be מתנה matneh to anyone ever. I mean, he
can't do that.
Well, okay, so those are good questions. But we'll take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara.
Exactly.
Now it is interesting though, you know, he doesn't have to say
don't go in private. His jealousy could go even beyond that. I
don't want to see you speaking to that guy. Clearly that's a
jealousy that's even beyond right, you know, and it could also be
a jealousy that he doesn't yet suspect her of doing anything wrong.
He's just as concerned about where things might
lead. Like, I saw you flirting with that guy, I saw you
talking to that guy, right? I don't want to see right, so
and so but that would be sufficient to be constitute a warning,
right, even if he's not yet suspecting her of having done it
or even if he's not telling her not to be in private,
even if it exceeds those types of concerns. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, and by the way, another interesting
thing to note in addition to how חז"ל Chazal have made this
more under judicial auspices is, you know, the Torah is not critical
of what a husband does. You know, besides the earlier question of
is it presuming she's guilty or not, but the Torah certainly does
not say anything about wrong about the man's actions. I mean, the
end of the פסוקים psukim is ונקה האיש מעון והאשה ההיא תשא
את עונה. v'nikah ha'ish me'avon v'ha'isha ha'hi tisa et avonah. So why
do you even have to say ונקה האיש מעון? v'nikah ha'ish me'avon?
Seems to be saying like he did nothing wrong about suspecting her,
right? Seems to be the פשט pshat way of reading this. So
we will see, you know, as we saw in נדרים, Nedarim, it's
so interesting, נדרים נזיר וסוטה, Nedarim, Nazir, v'Sotah, right, you know, that
are these good phenomenon or bad phenomenon? You know, so we saw
always this ambivalence around making נדרים nedarim and ambivalence around being a
נזיר, nazir, so we'll also see a similar questioning and ambivalence and
maybe even negativity towards the husband's acting in this type of a
way, which is not evident in the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מכדי, Michdi, it's some sometimes it's, in other words, it seems to
be counterpoint from antiquity around honor killings. In other words, there's
no...
right. Right. So in a way, that's a good point, similar to
controlling the גואל הדם go'el hadam already in the פסוקים psukim while
it hasn't been made judicial, it is controlling the complete vigilante honor
killings. That is correct, and that is a point that really needs
to be underscored. Right, at least it's saying you might have your
jealousy, you can't act on it. Like, here's the way you gotta
deal with it. Right, that's a very good point. Right, so already
in the פסוקים psukim it's controlling, you know, complete vigilante... right, exactly.
And the תורה שבעל פה Torah she'be'al peh makes it even more...
it can't be all the husband's jealousy, there has to be something
a little more objective.
Not just at that time, right, at this time too, towards the
women.
Right, exactly, exactly. Yep. Alright, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. מכדי. Michdi. תנא, Tana, everybody has more to say somehow about
סוטה Sotah than about נזיר, Nazir, I can't understand this. Okay. תנא,
Tana, okay, מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. תנא מנזיר סליק, tana
miNazir salik, the תנא tana just finished מסכת נזיר. Masechet Nazir. מאי
תנא דקתני סוטה, mai tana d'ka-tani Sotah,
why does סוטה Sotah follow נזיר? Nazir? Could be because it's the
only מסכת masechet left, but okay, in נשים, Nashim, but all right,
כדירבי, k'dei-Rabbi, like Rabbi. דתניא רבי אומר, d'tanya Rabbi omer, as the
ברייתא braita says, Rabbi says: למה נסמכה פרשת נזיר לפרשת סוטה, lama
nismacha parshat Nazir l'parshat Sotah, why in the Torah does נזיר Nazir
and סוטה Sotah juxtapose? Of course, there in the Torah of course
סוטה Sotah precedes נזיר. Nazir. לומר לך שכל הרואה סוטה בקלקולה, l'omar
lach shekol haro'eh Sotah b'kilkulah, to tell you that if somebody sees
a סוטה Sotah in her disgrace and he sees like what, you
know, how, what can happen if people sort of follow their desires,
יזיר עצמו מן היין, yazir atzmo min hayayin, it should lead to
him forswearing himself from wine, because, you know, wine then brings about,
becomes leads to indulgence and going ahead and, you know, can put
you on a bad path and acting in ways that you otherwise
would not act. So, wait, this does sound
like it's a good thing to be a נזיר.
nazir. Right. Anyway, okay, but that adds that order. That adds that
order. Notice, by the way, also, it's about the man, like it's
still הרואה יזיר עצמו. haro'eh yazir atzmo. So he sees what... Still,
it's so funny that even when it's about the woman sinning and
taking seed, it's about men taking heed from the woman's sin as
opposed to women taking. It's all, even here, it's like still from
the man's perspective.
But the woman can
be a נזירה Nezira too.
Exactly. Right. Did you finish קידושין Kiddushin and גיטין Gittin when I
was away last weekend?
Oh, I'm sorry, you're right. It's not the last one. It's the
last... you're right. You were away? Right, right. I don't know why
I said it was the last one. You're right. You're right, you're
right, it's the last in this
כרך. Kerach. You're right. I was too eager to move on to
נזיקין. Nezikin. You're right, you're right. Okay, good point. Good point. All
right, anyway, okay. So, איידי דתני סוטה והדר תני נזיר, Aidi detani
Sota vehadar tani Nazir, says סוטה Sota and then says נזיר, Nazir,
which is the order in the
פסוקים. Pesukim. So איידי דתני כתובות ותנא המדיר תנא נדרים. Aidi detani
Ketubot vetana Hamadir tana Nedarim. Now we're going to get a look
at the whole sequence. כתובות Ketubot talked about, one of the things
about כתובות Ketubot was the relationship of husband and wife and a
wife making vows and the husband annulling it. So that became a
nice segue into נדרים, Nedarim, although that wasn't at the very end
of כתובות, Ketubot, but it certainly is נדרים Nedarim relate to the
husband-wife marriage relationship. A lot of נדרים Nedarim is in the תורה,
Torah, it's the פרשה Parsha about husband and wife and annulling vows.
Okay, so that was a logical follow-up from כתובות. Ketubot. ואיידי דתני
נדרים תנא נזיר דדמי לנדרים. Va'aidi detani Nedarim tana Nazir dedami lenedarim.
What's it going to be about? נדרים Nedarim are going to talk
about נזיר, Nazir, which is a type of a נדר. Neder. ותני
סוטה כדי רבי. Vetani Sota kiderabbi. And once we had that, now
we have סוטה Sota that follows נזיר, Nazir, just as it does
sort of in the תורה. Torah. It's juxtaposed. The order is reversed
because of the logical sort of move of כתובות, Ketubot, נדרים, Nedarim,
נזיר Nazir as a unit and then moving on to סוטה. Sota.
Now, of course, also the reason is, as I always say when
we begin a מסכת, Masechet, that it's the number of פרקים. Perakim.
It's the size of the מסכת Masechet that determines, like the bigger
מסכתות Masechtot defined by number of פרקים Perakim come earlier. But that
being said, how many פרקים Perakim are there in סוטה? Sota? About
ten? Nine, I think.
Nine.
And how many were there in נזיר? Nazir? There were nine. Okay,
so you see, you still need to answer the question, because they're
both nine, so you could have had סוטה Sota come first. And
it really is true that there sort of is a logical sequence:
כתובות, Ketubot, נדרים, Nedarim, נזיר Nazir as a unit and then moving
on to סוטה. Sota. Okay, so now let's go on.
המקנא, Hamakane, a man who is jealous of his wife or warns
his wife. דיעבד ולא לכתחילה. Di'eved velo lechatchila. This sounds like only
if he's doing it, but not that he should do it. רש"י
Rashi says it could have said it a different way. It could
have said, רבי אליעזר אומר מקנא אדם לאשתו על פי שנים. Rabbi
Eliezer omer makane adam leishto al pi shenayim. It says המקנא, Hamakane,
he's already doing it. Let's talk about how it gets done. But
it sounds like it's דיעבד. di'eved. תוספות Tosafot points out that very
often it says ה-X Ha-X and it doesn't mean דיעבד. di'eved. ההולך
לשחוט את הפסח. Haholech lishchot et hapesach. Okay, that doesn't mean it's
דיעבד. di'eved. So again, the fact that the גמרא Gemara is choosing
to read this as a דיעבד, di'eved, maybe again because it could
have framed it differently, but maybe because the גמרא Gemara is already
inclined to be disapproving of this as we will see.
Yes, you have a מצוה Mitzvah on doing that, but somewhere else,
but we know it's
not.
Right, but there are some that are going to say it's a
מצוה Mitzvah לקנאות את אשתו, lekanot et ishto, you know. But yes,
but yes, that's basically what תוספות Tosafot says. He says, look, when
it's possible to read it as a לכתחילה lechatchila or whatever, when
it's clear, we'll read it that way. But here, but that is
the elsewhere
where it tells you to do that thing that makes it, right,
makes it clear
it's a לכתחילה lechatchila thing and then since we don't
have that anywhere here, we regard it as. Right, so that's essentially
what תוספות Tosafot says. But it could also be that the גמרא
Gemara is inclined to try to read this in a disapproving way.
So let's take a look. Right, but it could be that there's
a real linguistic, grammatical thing the גמרא Gemara is picking up. Right,
exactly. המקנא דיעבד ולא לכתחילה קסבר תנא דידן אסור לקנאות. Hamakane di'eved
velo lechatchila kasavar tana didan assur lekanot. Right, so right at the
outset, with very little textual basis, the גמרא Gemara puts out there
the first explanation, the first thing you hear in this מסכת Masechet
is אסור לקנאות. assur lekanot. I think that's pretty powerful. Those are
the first first thing you hear, אסור לקנאות. assur lekanot. So you're
not allowed to do this procedure. Okay, אמר רב שמואל בר רב
יצחק כי הוי פתח ריש לקיש בסוטה. Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav
Yitzchak ki hava patach Resh Lakish beSota. When Resh Lakish would begin
learning, now is it מסכת סוטה Masechet Sota or רש"י Rashi says
he would talk about סוטה, Sota, the פרשת סוטה, Parshat Sota, he
was giving a דרשה drasha in שול. shul. אמר הכי. Amar hachi.
Here's what he would say. And caution, when they would give like
a דרשה, drasha, they would start with אגדתא Agadeta and so on.
So, אין מזווגין לו לאדם אשה אלא לפי מעשיו. Ein mezavgin lo
leadam isha ela lefi maasav. The, again, interestingly using the wine metaphor
in the juxtaposition to נזיר. Nazir. So to למזוג כוסות limzog kosot
is to pour a glass of wine, to mix it with water.
Anyway, heaven does not sort of mix, sort of match up with
a person, pour for a man a woman except...
אלא לפי מעשיו מזווגין, ela lefi maasav mezavgin, right?
Oh, זיווג. zivug. Right. Oh, I'm thinking of מוזגין. mozgin. I don't
know what's with me today. Okay, what? It could be a play
on words.
Yeah,
but I think you're right, it would... but it would have been
מוזגין. mozgin. I think you're right. זיווג. zivug. Right. Okay, all right.
It's not just a glass of wine. Right.
Okay. Okay, okay, anyway, I don't know what's with me this morning.
All right. אין מזווגין לו לאדם אשה אלא לפי מעשיו. Ein Mezavgin
lo leadam isha ela lefi ma'asav. A person is only matched up
with a man, I mean with a woman, according to his actions,
according to his deeds, שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי לא ינוח שבט הרשע על
גורל הצדיקים, Ki lo yanuach shevet harasha al goral hatzaddikim, because the
staff, the lot of the wicked will not fall
in the lot of the righteous. So if you are if you're
a righteous person, then you're not going to get something that's deserving
for wicked people. Which means what?
Which means that your wife wouldn't have gone to do all this
unless you were bad to begin with.
Which means that if you're about to publicly be jealous about your
wife, what are you communicating and broadcasting to the rest of the
world? That you must have deserved a wife like that, right? So
it's like on the one hand, if this is happening to you,
what did you do wrong to deserve it? But I think it
also very much plays, so
again, like if you think about it in conversation to the פסוקים
Pesukim about
ונקה האיש מעון, V'nikah ha'ish me'avon, right? And this is sort of
saying, ah no, if he's going ahead and this is what his
wife is doing, you gotta wonder what he did and what type
of a person he is. So it's almost like exactly not ונקה.
V'nikah. What does it reflect about him? And then one also wonders
what the message is about
אסור לקנאות, Asur lekannot, like if you better think twice because you're
going to be saying something about who you are as well, not
just about who she is, yes.
Right, so that
a
husband couldn't do that if he didn't have some level of purity.
Right, right. So that the waters wouldn't work if he himself had
sinned. Okay, right. But so that's if in fact he had, this
is more like of a theological statement, but if this is a
people's belief, then that will
impact. So that's what I think. I think that this is a
way of making people really think, men really think twice before they
go ahead and do
this. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar
Bar Hana Amar Rabbi Yohanan, קשה מזווגם כקריעת ים סוף. Kashah mezavgam
k'kriat Yam Suf. It is as difficult to match them correctly as
the splitting of the sea, okay, because how do you get a
perfect match? שנאמר, Shene'emar, right, very appropriate now with the whole שידוך
Shidduch crisis. קשה מזווגם כקריעת ים סוף. Kashah mezavgam k'kriat Yam Suf.
שנאמר אלוהים מושיב יחידים ביתה. Shene'emar Elokim moshiv yechidim baitah. God makes
the individuals dwell at the home, so it takes two individuals and
makes them set up a home, matches them, and creates a בית.
Bayit. Okay, מוציא אסירים בכושרות, Motzi asirim bakosharot, like as from removing
those that are bound, to what does בכושרות Bakosharot mean? Does it
mean from their chains? רש"י Rashi says it means in the, right,
that's what I think פשט Pshat is. רש"י Rashi says it means
at the right time, like
he brought them out in the spring, it was a nice time.
But anyway, yeah
exactly.
This
is real רש"י, Rashi, yeah. So that's what I was saying initially
that that's why תוספות Tosafot is normal because רש"י's Rashi back. So
anyway, but קריעת ים סוף, Kriat Yam Suf,
right?
So you see so God took them out, so talking about like
קריעת ים סוף Kriat Yam Suf and יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, and
that is being compared
to finding two individuals and creating a match. איני, Ini, is this
really
true? והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, V'ha'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, ארבעים
יום קודם יצירת הולד בת קול יוצאת ואומרת, Arba'im yom kodem yetzirat
havlad bat kol yotzei v'omerat, בת פלוני לפלוני בית פלוני לפלוני שדה
פלוני לפלוני. Bat ploni l'ploni bayit ploni l'ploni sadeh ploni l'ploni. That
40 days before the child is formed, what's the significance of 40
days before the child is formed? What happens 40 days before the
child is formed?
That's conception.
It's when it's conceived. Right, it's the sense is that 40 days
after conception is when it becomes like considered a fetus and it's
not just מיא בעלמא Maya b'alma in one phrase of the גמרא.
Gemara. That's the beginning of the forming of the child is 40
days after conception, so this means at the moment of conception. Okay,
so at the moment of
conception, a heavenly voice comes out and says the daughter of so-and-so
will go to פלוני, Ploni, and he'll get such and such a
house, and he'll get such and such a field. So why is
this a question? Because if the match is לפי מעשיו, Lefi ma'asav,
then then you can't do the match yet because you don't know
yet what his מעשים Ma'asim will be because there's בחירה חופשית Bechirah
chofshit and
הכל בידי שמים חוץ מיראת שמים. Hakol bidei shamayim chutz miyirat shamayim.
So this מדרש Midrash in a way, it speaks about like as
a בת קול Bat Kol and it might speak about מזל, Mazel,
but this מדרש Midrash can easily be translated into the reality about
how so much of our life is predetermined for us before we're
born. I mean it certainly was that way in the ancient world
when there was like very little choice and very little mobility and
so on. But even nowadays, right, your genetics so has a lot
to do with your character and your intelligence, whatever are you being
born into, what type of a family, right, upper middle class, poor,
what type of education are you going to receive, what type of
society are you going to live in? So much is predetermined already
before you even come out into this world and that seems to...
be what this מדרש Midrash is saying, right, at the moment of
conception, right, it's always like, are you going to be a, you
know, are you, I, you know, what type of field are you
going to get, what type of house are you going to get?
But interestingly, it also says what type of woman are you going
to marry. Now, how is that fated? Okay, and this is the
idea of, now, by the way, I should say another מדרש Midrash
says, is this child going to be a חכם Chacham or רשע,
Rasha, עשיר Ashir or עני? Oni? And then it says, so the
גמרא Gemara and all these other things, so the גמרא Gemara says,
wait a minute, I get everything else, עשיר Ashir or עני, Oni,
this or that, not חכם Chacham or טיפש, Tipesh, that I get,
but how could it be צדיק Tzadik or רשע? Rasha? What happened
to בחירה חופשית? Bechira Chofshis? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, take
out צדיק Tzadik or רשע, Rasha, right? So you know, so again,
like everything is fated except what are your actions going to be,
right? That the גמרא Gemara is very clear, that's totally בחירה חופשית.
Bechira Chofshis. So here, how could we speak about the match being
fated if it's לפי מעשיו? Lefi Maasav? Those two don't work together.
Okay, and so the question
was, isn't it hard, because meaning like, it was so hard, then
הנה, Hinnei, how's God already knowing?
No, no, that's not the way you'll see, that's not the, that
doesn't seem to be the פשט. Pshat. רש״י Rashi says, especially if
you know that another גמרא Gemara sort of explicitly eliminates from this
list צדיק Tzadik and רשע, Rasha, like really it's the point like
that's not determined. So if it's לפי מעשיו, Lefi Maasav, how could
that be fated? So on the one hand, it's the idea of
בשערט, Bashert, but it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara doesn't think that
בשערט Bashert is equal to, you know, your worthiness and your deeds
and your character, well, maybe character but not deeds. Okay, so let's
take a look.
But wait, I thought didn't we just say a second before, קשין
קריעת ים סוף, Kashin Krias Yam Suf, and then איני, Aini, so
then איני's Aini not going קשין קריעת ים סוף, Kashin Krias Yam
Suf, it's going on the thing before it?
Yeah, that's the way רש״י Rashi understands. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, לא קשיא הא בזיווג ראשון הא בזיווג שני. Lo kashya, ha
bezig rishon, ha bezig sheini. First marriage or second marriage. The first
marriage is בשערט, Bashert, is the בת קול שיוצאת. Bas Kol sheyotzei.
The second marriage is לפי מעשיו, Lefi Maasav, which is like what?
So like you only get the spouse you deserve if you have
a second marriage? The first spouse is based on some type of
a fate, you know, and are you telling me that like, that
the whole idea of בשערט Bashert is that it's not a good
match necessarily, it's just what's like somehow destined because of life's circumstances?
I mean, it's very hard to come up with a satisfying sort
of like theological, religious resolution to, no, it can't be because the
לפי מעשיו Lefi Maasav is the whole point that it hasn't happened
yet. So that's number one. Actually, in some of the I saw
some of the מפרשים Meforshim actually ask, actually, it's תוספות שאנץ Tosafos
Shantz I think says, he says, it does, I don't know, it's
one of the בעלי התוספות, Baalei HaTosafos, okay, it's probably from the
students of the ראש משאנץ, Rash MiShantz, okay, which anyway, so Sens,
right, which is a town in Germany. So anyway, the point is,
he says it's only לפי מעשיו Lefi Maasav if it's a second
marriage for both of them, because presumably, if it's not a second
marriage for both of them, for one of them, it's still who
they were fated for. Of course the, that's interesting because this whole
thing is being said from the man's perspective. So you might have
said, the woman doesn't get anything fated, it's just like the man,
right? It's לפי מעשיו, Lefi Maasav, לפי Lefi his fate. So once
he's onto a second marriage, it could be her first, but you
know, but it's interesting that he sort of balances it along those
lines of like, of like, whose perspective is it? Look at תוספות,
Tosafos, קודם יצירת הולד. Kodem Yetziras HaValad.
תוספות Tosafos says, נראה לרבי, Nireh LeRebbi, קודם יצירת הזכר, Kodem Yetziras
HaZachar, ביני אם לא נולדה נקבה עדיין ביני אם נולדה. beini im
lo nolada nekeiva adayin beini im nolada. Like because it says, so
it's all basically the man is the one being matched up and
you know, maybe he also was dealing with the reality we're dealing
with, which is, is that if they married younger women, so that
he was dealing with that reality. So how could you have matched
them up if the woman hadn't been created yet? So somewhat the
מהרש״א Marsha wants to say that's why it says בת פלוני לפלוני,
bas ploni leploni, because you don't even know yet she's not, you
just know it'll be that man's daughter, but she hasn't yet even
come into existence yet. So somewhat the תוספות, Tosafos, oh yeah, I
don't know. Anyway, so again, it's, it is interesting, obviously the whole
male perspective and how this then, this then doesn't help the ריש
לקיש's Reish Lakish the whole nice דרשה Drasha about סוטה. Sotah. Because
then if you know, certainly in those times most people were only
on a first marriage, I mean, I guess later in life it
could be because there was a lot of death in childbirth, but
anyway, but like you know, there certainly was a lot less divorce,
right? So so to say, oh well, the first marriage is not
לפי מעשיו, Lefi Maasav, it does then, it doesn't help for פרשת
סוטה Parshas Sotah for everybody who's on a first marriage, right? It
doesn't say anything about that. So it's clearly that that was not
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish intention. The גמרא Gemara is trying to reconcile
two different מדרשים, Midrashim, but clearly ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish intention was,
you know, was to say that it's always לפי מעשיו. Lefi Maasav.
And again, when we sort of imagine the idea of בשערט, Bashert,
we imagine בשערט Bashert because it's the right person, right? It's not
just somehow fated, but it's fated because somehow it's the right match.
It's the קשין זיווגין, Kashin Zivugin, right? This is putting all of
that onto the second marriage and making the first one somewhat arbitrary,
or seems to be, right? So it's hard to sort of deal
with this גמרא Gemara that tries to bring these two together. All
right, let's continue. רבי אלעזר אומר. Rabbi Elazar Omer. All right, let's
continue. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, מכאן אלא
לפי שנים.
mikan ela
l'fi shnayim. עד כאן לא פליגי, ad kan lo pligi, says the
גמרא, Gemara, אלא בקינוי וסתירה. ela bekinuy vestira. So they're only arguing
whether קינוי, kinuy, whether the warning and the going into hiding, actually
not even we're arguing about the warning, the warning they agree is
two, and then they're debating about whether the hiding, the hiding, the
going into private needs two or one. אבל בטומאה, aval betuma, if
there was somebody to testify directly that she had committed adultery, not
just she went into private into private into a private place, but
that she said I saw them commit adultery, so then עד אחד
מהימן, ed echad meheman, presumably one witness would be believed. Now, how
do you know that? Like תוספות Tosafot says, what do you mean?
Maybe, think about it, if one witness says she committed adultery, you
don't we're going to find out, you don't make her drink the
water. You only make her drink the water if you have a
doubt. If a witness says she committed adultery, we're going to say
like if it's not two witnesses, so we're not going to kill
her, right, we don't have that type of witness what we're going
to say we assume then we're going to say then we'll treat
it as if she definitely did, again, not enough to prosecute but
enough to say that she gets divorced without a כתובה, kesuvah, she
can't drink the water and all those things. So תוספות Tosafot says,
how do you know that everybody would agree to a lower standard?
Maybe because the consequence is so final, everybody would demand a higher
standard of two witnesses. So there's really nothing in the משנה Mishna
that makes it clear that if it's about direct testimony whether one
would suffice. So תוספות Tosafot basically says, yeah, because we're going to
have a ברייתא Baraita that says that, so we're really just doing
a lead in to that ברייתא. Baraita. But we could have just
as easily have said that you needed actually two because of the
more severe consequences of that testimony. All right, so anyway, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara is saying. But when it comes to testifying,
one is supposed one is believed, and again by the way I
should also mention, this one who is believed is with a backdrop
of קינוי וסתירה. kinuy vestira. If one guy just shows up and
says I saw this woman commit adultery, it's like he you know
I mean there's גמרות Gemaras where basically like they laugh at a
guy because of that because of מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra.
So it's actually he's only believed when it builds on the foundation
of קינוי וסתירה. kinuy vestira. If you take so if you take
a look, רש"י Rashi says that explicitly. רש"י Rashi says מנלן
דמהימן עד אחד, minalan de'meheman ed echad, it's six lines from the
bottom, רש"י Rashi says בטומאה של סתירה אחר קינוי, betuma shel stira
achar kinuy, only if only if there was a קינוי, kinuy, there
was a סתירה, stira, then he comes and he says I saw
her commit adultery. And with this person, what with this oh
presumably right with this person. Okay, so we so that's really not
hinted to in the משנה Mishna but we're coming with an assumption
that that's the הלכה. halacha. We're using this as an opportunity to
put that on the table that if there's an עד אחד ed
echad to the adultery that follow to the act following the warning
that we believe the עד אחד ed echad enough that she's divorced
and loses her כתובה. kesuvah. So בטומאה עד אחד מהימן. betuma ed
echad meheman. ותנן נמי, u'tnan nami, עד אחד אומר אני ראיתי שנטמאת,
ed echad omer ani raiti shenitmet, so here's really why we say
it, not clearly like really how we know this. One witness says
that I became that I saw her become טמאה, tmeiah, לא הייתה
שותה, lo haita shota, she wouldn't drink and we would just assume,
you know, take him at his word and she'd get divorced without
a כתובה, kesuvah, he would be believed.
So מדאורייתא מנלן דמהימן עד אחד, mid'oraita minalan de'meheman ed echad, how
do you know one witness is believed in this type of a
case?
דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabanan, because we taught,
ועד אין בה והיא לא נתפשה. v'ed ein ba vehi lo nitpasa.
Okay, so it says he suspects his wife but there's no witness
to it to the fact and she was not raped, okay, and
then it goes on. That's the פרשה parsha of סוטה. Sotah. So
it says בשנים הכתוב מדבר, bishnayim hakatuv medaber, means that there are
not two witnesses. או אינה אלא אפילו באחד, o eina ela afilu
be'echad, maybe it means there's not even one witness? תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar, it says עד ed in the singular, you learned תלמוד לומר
לא יקום עד אחד באיש, talmud lomar lo yakum ed echad be'ish,
one man cannot rise up against a person, one witness cannot rise
up against a person. ממשמע שנאמר לא יקום עד באיש, mimashma shene'emar
lo yakum ed be'ish, it could have just said an עד ed
should not rise up against a person. איני יודע שהוא אחד, eini
yodea shehu echad, so of course we're talking about even one man,
once it would say it in the singular, one witness. מה תלמוד
לומר אחד, ma talmud lomar echad, why does it have to say
one witness? זה בנין אב, ze binyan av, this becomes a paradigm.
כל מקום שנאמר עד הרי כאן שנים, kol makom shene'emar ed harei
kan shnayim, from this we can infer because it saw fit to
say אחד, echad, that the word עד ed by itself הרי כאן
שנים, harei kan shnayim, means a means a group of עדים, edim,
two עדים edim that would have the full weight of witnesses. Okay,
so therefore because it said אחד, echad, I learned that עד ed
by itself means two witnesses. Very universal principle of how the גמרא
Gemara reads the פסוקים, psukim, that עד ed by itself means two
witnesses.
Pretty amazing דרשה. drasha.
Yeah, so עד שפרט לך הכתוב אחד, ad shepirit lecha hakatuv echad,
until the Torah tells you one, but עד ed by itself means
two. ואמר רחמנא, v'amar rachmana, תרי לית בה אלא חד, trei leis
ba ela chad, so it says ועד אין בה, v'ed ein ba,
now we're going to say it means there are no two there
aren't two witnesses against her, there's one witness against her. Okay, והיא
לא נתפשה, vehi lo nitpasa, and she hasn't been raped, so if
it's saying there's only one witness against her and she hasn't been
a case of rape, so therefore presumably the consequence is אסורה, asura,
the witness is believed and she's It's forbidden. Now again, that is
a strange read of the פסוקים. pesukim. Because the פסוקים pesukim say,
ועד אין בה והיא לא נתפשה, ve'ed ein bah vehi lo nitpasha,
והביא האיש את אשתו, vehevi ha'ish et ishto, right? Because there are,
because there aren't witnesses, he has to go through the ritual of
Sotah. Yes, that's what the פסוקים pesukim say. Yes, everybody with me?
Right? That's what the פסוקים pesukim say. Where is the גמרא Gemara
saying, oh, there aren't two witnesses, there's one witness, oh, in that
case don't go through the ritual of Sotah, we'll assume she did
it? Right? So besides you know reading in the פסוק pasuk that
there's one witness, it reads a new concept, a new like law
about that. And if there's one witness then it's going to be
even more severe, we're going to assume she did it and you
don't go through the ritual of Sotah. Okay, so that's how we're
reading it.
Okay, אלא טעמא, ela ta'ama, now the גמרא Gemara is just going
to figure out the, you know, let's just get to the two
dots. It'll figure out what it could have said. אלא טעמא דכתב
לא יקום עד אחד באיש, ela ta'ama dechtav lo yakum ed echad
be'ish, it's because it wrote לא יקום עד אחד. lo yakum ed
echad. הלאו הכי הוה אמינא עד דסוטה חד הוא. halav hachi hava
amina ed desota chad hu. So now it's going back to say
you only knew the word עד ed meant two witnesses because of
this other פסוק pasuk that taught you that עד ed means, I
mean that you only knew that עד ed meant two witnesses because
of this other פסוק pasuk that tells you the word עד ed
always means two witnesses. Okay, if it weren't for that other פסוק,
pasuk, I would have said ועד אין בה ve'ed ein bah means
there isn't even one witness against her, right? That's how I most
likely would have read the פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara says,
how could I have read it that way? ואי אפילו חד ליתא,
ve'afilu chad leita, if there isn't even one witness, אלא במאי מיתסרא,
ela bemai mitsra, how does she become forbidden? Now again, it's a
strange question because the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is because
there's no witnesses, he has to bring her to the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. But we're reading the פסוק, pasuk, there's not two witnesses
and she wasn't raped and therefore she's forbidden. Somehow we're reading in
this other thing in the פסוק pasuk that in this case don't
bring her to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, she's forbidden. So it
says, of course it means that there was not two but one,
because if there were no witnesses, why would she be forbidden?
Okay, so איצטריך. itztrich. No, I needed from this other פסוק pasuk
to tell me that עד ed meant two. Why?
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, no,
here's what
I would have needed the פסוק pasuk to explicitly say that you
needed two, which is not the הלכה, halacha, but here's why I
would have needed it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would
have thought to say even if the פסוק pasuk had said nothing,
I would have thought maybe here we should believe one. Why here
should we believe one? Because סוטה שאני, Sota shani, here it's different
than normal cases. דרגלים לדבר, deraglayim ladavar, that you should remember that
from just a few days ago in נזיר. Nazir. Because there's circumstantial
evidence, there's a good basis to presume it. So had the תורה
Torah said, so I would have said naturally I would have said
one would have been believed, and maybe that's why the תורה Torah
would have to tell me don't believe one, you need two. Now
שהרי קינא לה ונסתרה, sheharei kina lah venistara, what's the רגלים לדבר?
raglayim ladavar? He warned her and she disregarded his warning. The warning
isn't enough, the warning might just be his own jealousy. But it's
the combination of the disregarding and going into private following the fact
that he warned her and was suspicious, all of that means we
got to look into this. להמיניה עד אחד, lehaminei ed echad, then
I would have thought to believe one. So it could have been
the תורה Torah telling me don't believe one, you need two, because
I would have had a reason to believe one. The funny thing
is that that actually is the הלכה, halacha, right? Remember, the הלכה
halacha winds up being we do believe one witness here. Normally we
need two witnesses and at the end of the day we're saying
here we believe
one. Why we believe one witness? By the כי קאמרי דאיתסרו. ki
ka'amrei d'it'asru. So the גמרא Gemara is telling you רגלים לדבר. Raglayim
L'davar. So right here, the גמרא's Gemara introduced two major points about
מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. Number one, אסור לקנאות Asur L'kanos and raising
that question, right, about she shouldn't be doing it, not raising the
question, raising the issue that it's a bad thing. And number two,
explaining why it actually all of this makes sense because of רגלים
לדבר. Raglayim L'davar. That's why we go through with the ritual. That's
why an עד אחד ed echad would be believed because of רגלים
לדבר. Raglayim L'davar. Yeah?
The one witness... is the circumstantial evidence based on the one witness
that...
No, no, the circumstantial evidence is based on the two witnesses that
he warned her and then she went into private. Well, that depends,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. Okay, so some
of that might also be one witness, but it is based on
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. But then in
addition to all of that, a witness then says she committed adultery,
right. Well let me just... Okay, you know what, it's already 8:30,
so I'm just going to read the last sentence. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, והא מדכתיב והיא
לא נתפשה, v'ha midichtiv v'hee lo nitpasa, ומי מצית אמרת, u'mi matzis
amrat, דאין נאמן בה
ושריה. d'ain ne'eman bah u'sharya. How could I have thought to read
the פסוק pasuk to mean don't believe one and therefore she'll be
permitted? That would have been the hypothetical read of the פסוק. pasuk.
והא מדכתיב והיא לא נתפשה, v'ha midichtiv v'hee lo nitpasa, it says
she wasn't raped. מכלל דאסורה, miklul d'asura, the point of the פסוק
pasuk is to tell you that she's forbidden because she's not raped
is an aggravating fact, I mean we assume she did it. No,
איצטריך, itztrich, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina,
I would have thought to read the פסוק pasuk the following way:
אין נאמן בה, ain ne'eman bah, one witness is not believed, עד
דאיכא תרי, ad d'ika trei,
you need two, and if you have two, then she'll be
guilty. ובדתריי נמי היא דלא נתפשה, u'v'trei nami hee d'lo nitpasa, she'll
be guilty if she hasn't been raped. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, don't
read the פסוק pasuk that way. So all this was a hypothetical.
Don't read the פסוק, pasuk, we read the פסוק pasuk that there're
not two witnesses, there's one witness and one witness and she hasn't
been raped, that's enough to assume that she did it and she
would not drink the waters. So one witness of having committed adultery
already determines that she's guilty to the point not that she gets
prosecuted but she gets divorced without a כתובה. ketubah.